Yes, that long last that stinky Cold
War's finally coming to an end and I
reckon we ought to talk about it. So, if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milked perestroika style, then let's get
to it. Okay, so the first thing you need
to know is that the Cold War officially
ended with the collapse of the Soviet
Union in 1991. And if you're keeping
score, that's 3 years after the end of
Ronald Reagan's second term. But, even
though the conflict didn't officially
end on his watch, Reagan definitely
played a big role in bringing the war to
a close and he did so by means of at
least four strategies. The first
strategy Reagan used was a series of
speeches. Now, love him or hate him,
it's hard to deny that Ronald Reagan
possessed a profound gift for flapping
his mouth hole in a way that made
Americans and the world sit up and
listen. For example, Reagan delivered a
particularly influential speech to the
British Parliament in 1982, which became
known as his Westminster address. Now,
he gave this speech right at the moment
when Cold War intensity had been revived
after the Soviet Union had invaded
Afghanistan in order to prop up the
failing communist regime. And as you
should expect by now, the United States
and its allies were supporting the
anti-communist rebels and that marked a
significant departure from the period of
relative détente in the 1970s.
Therefore, Reagan used this speech to
explain that the long-standing policy of
containing the spread of communism was
no longer viable, but instead communism
must be rolled back and eventually
extinguished entirely. Part of his
reasoning here was that totalitarian
communism was by nature doomed to fail,
while democracy, morally superior in
every way, was fated to cover the earth.
Or as Reagan himself put it, the forward
march of freedom and democracy will
leave Marxism-Leninism on the ash heap
of history. And then a year later,
Reagan gave another speech in which he
called the Soviet Union an evil empire
and claimed that it was the focus of
evil in the modern world. So, yeah,
about as subtle as a stomach pump. And
the point to remember is that these
kinds of speeches indicated that Reagan
was intentionally reframing the conflict
as more than just ideological. Anyway,
this idea became a significant
development in what became known as the
Reagan Doctrine, which significantly
shaped his administration's Cold War
foreign policy. And basically, the
doctrine said that the United States
would provide overt and covert
assistance to anti-communist rebels who
fought to overthrow communist regimes.
And maybe you're confused right now,
because doesn't that sound exactly like
the Truman doctrine but with better
hair? Well, I won't dispute the better
hair part on account of I myself have no
moral standing to pass judgments on
other people's hair, but the Reagan
doctrine was both similar to and
different from the Truman doctrine. It
was similar in that the United States
pledged support for anti-communist
forces fighting against communist
infiltration, but it was different in
that the Truman doctrine aimed only to
prevent communism from spreading and did
so through intensive US involvement,
like for example in the Korean and
Vietnam War. But by Reagan's
administration, the Vietnam War had left
the majority of Americans feeling weary
and bitter of sending US troops across
the world to fight communism. And so the
Reagan doctrine pledged support less in
terms of troops and more in terms of
money and weapons and training. And most
important, the goal of the Reagan
doctrine was not the containment of
communism, but the rollback and defeat
of communism. And then in 1987, Reagan
traveled to Germany in order to deliver
a speech at the Berlin Wall, which had
long been a symbol of the division
between Western democracy and Soviet
repression. And here Reagan acknowledged
that the new Soviet leader Mikhail
Gorbachev had indeed introduced some
freedoms back into Soviet society and
that was a good thing. But then Reagan
asked whether these freedoms represented
real progress toward freedom or just a
way to calm people down and further
consolidate power for the Soviet regime.
And to further make his point, Reagan
made sure that the speakers that
amplified his speech were pointed at
both West Berliners in the crowd and
over the wall toward East Berliners as
well. And then Reagan challenged the
Soviet leader to prove his goodwill
toward his people with this phrase, "Mr.
Gorbachev, tear down this wall." Anyway,
the point is through his speeches,
Reagan was able to skillfully frame the
Cold War as a battle between good and
evil and that proved to be an
exceedingly effective strategy. And then
Reagan's second strategy included an
increase in military spending. So on
this count, Reagan led the federal
government into massive spending on
military and technological development,
the most notable of which was the
Strategic Defense Initiative, which
aimed to create defense systems in space
that shot down missiles with, wait for
it, lasers. And that's why not
surprisingly, the critics of the SDI
were fond of calling the program Star
Wars, which hey, you know, if I'm
Reagan, ultimate compliment. But anyway,
this level of military spending drove
the US into significant debt, but it was
Reagan's belief that peace could only
come through strength on the part of the
US. And even though the SDI never came
to pass, it represented a growing divide
between the US and the Soviet Union.
Reagan believed that the Soviets would
attempt to match the US spending in
terms of weapons development, and in
large part he was right. But, the
problem is that since the 1970s, the
Soviet economy had been stagnant thanks
to a variety of factors like political
corruption and falling oil prices, and
therefore could not match that kind of
spending. And therefore, the Soviet
attempts to keep up with US military and
technological investment led them into
further economic decline, which
contributed to its own demise. And then
third, Reagan engaged in a series of
diplomatic efforts with the Soviets. For
example, in 1985, Reagan met for the
first time with Soviet leader Mikhail
Gorbachev at the Geneva Summit. And the
goal of the meetings was to address the
increasing danger of the ongoing arms
race and establish a working diplomatic
relationship between the two leaders.
And while no treaty was signed as a
result of the summit, it did lead to two
very important outcomes. First, it
marked a significant turning point in
US-Soviet Cold War relations. You see,
up to this point, the relationship had
been mostly characterized by tension and
deep mistrust. But, after this meeting,
both leaders established a precedent for
more open communication and ongoing
negotiations. And then second, it laid
the foundation for future agreements
that would have a significant impact on
the reduction of nuclear weapons on both
sides. For example, in 1987, Reagan and
Gorbachev signed the Intermediate-Range
Nuclear Forces Treaty or INF, in which
both sides agreed to abolish an entire
category of nuclear weapons from their
arsenals and thus marked a significant
de-escalation of the Cold War arms race.
And to be clear, this treaty was just
one in a series of agreements between
the two powers aimed at limiting the
scope of the arms race. The first one
being SALT I and the second being SALT
II, which we talked all about in Unit 8.
And then fourth, Reagan engaged in many
limited military interventions. So,
right in line with the Reagan Doctrine,
the president authorized several covert
operations that aimed to roll back
communism, and I'll just tell you about
the campaign in Nicaragua. So, long
story short, in 1979, a group of
revolutionaries known as the Sandinistas
overthrew the Nicaraguan dictator and
assumed power. And once in power, the
Sandinistas made significant political
and economic changes along the lines of
socialism with support from communist
Cuba and the Soviet Union. And unless
you've been asleep for the last like 20
videos, you'll know that such a
development made US policy makers real
twitchy. So in response, the US invested
heavily although covertly in another
group that sought to oust the
Sandinistas, namely the Contras.
However, Congress having recently
attempted to reclaim its war making
powers from the executive branch after
the Vietnam war, went ahead and put the
legislative kibosh on this operation.
And to do this, they passed the Boland
Amendment which prohibited the US from
providing direct aid to the Contras. And
so Reagan was disappointed and said,
"Well, Congress is the people's house.
They have spoken and I shall obey."
Wouldn't that be hilarious if Reagan was
like that? No, top officials in Reagan's
administration got to work real fast
hatching a plan to circumvent the
congressional prohibition. So as it
turned out, the administration was also
supporting the Iranian government in its
fight against Iraq by selling them
American made munitions through Israel.
So Reagan's officials decided to take
the inflated profits from the Iranian
arms sales and covertly funnel it to
support the Nicaraguan Contras in their
fight against communism. Now eventually
this scheme was made public by a
Lebanese newspaper and Congress launched
an investigation which ultimately led to
the dismissal of several of Reagan's top
officials. Regardless, the resulting war
in Nicaragua lasted seven years and cost
tens of thousands of lives and was
ultimately ended in 1989 with a
ceasefire and military demobilization
agreement. Okay, now an equally
important cause to the end of the Cold
War were the seismic political and
economic changes going on over in the
Soviet Union itself. So in 1985, Mikhail
Gorbachev came to power in the Soviet
Union and several of his reform policies
contributed greatly to the collapse of
the Soviet Union. First policy was known
as perestroika which was a restructuring
of the economy to address all their
economic woes by reducing the level of
central planning from the government.
And the second policy was known as
glasnost which when being translated
means open. And under this policy, the
Soviet government committed to less
secrecy and more transparency while
easing up on their policies of
censorship and suppression of dissent.
And then third, Gorbachev announced that
the Soviet Union would no longer use
military intervention in order to prop
up communist governments in Eastern
Europe. And with those developments in
place, satellite states in the Eastern
Bloc took quick advantage of the
loosening grip of the Soviet Union. So,
nationalistic reform movements erupted
in one Eastern European country after
another, and that led to similar reform
movements across the Soviet Union as
people in Lithuania, and Georgia, and
other states began declaring
independence and breaking free from
Soviet control. And then, in 1989, the
Berlin Wall was torn down, and Germany
was reunited. And in response to all
those destabilizing forces, the Soviet
legislature voted in 1991 to dissolve
the Soviet Union, thus marking an end to
the Cold War. And so, after the collapse
of the Soviet Union, the United States
was the only remaining superpower in the
world. And over the next couple of
decades, Americans would attempt to
reckon with the role they played in a
post-Cold War world. So, President
George H.W. Bush proclaimed that the end
of the Cold War marked the beginning of
a new world order. And there were
several means by which the US asserted
its power in order to preserve that
order to its own liking, two of which
are going to need to know. First of all,
the US engaged in new military
interventions after the Cold War, but
for different reasons. So, all the
various conflicts that occurred during
the Cold War were about containing or
rolling back communist influence. After
the Cold War, the US engaged in
conflicts to keep its own global power
and influence safe. And to tell you the
truth, both of those are basically
saying the same thing. The only subtle
difference is that during the Cold War,
the US intervened throughout the world
in the name of containing communism. And
then, after the Cold War, the US
intervened in the name of protecting and
supporting democracy. And I'll give you
two examples here real quick. First was
the American invasion of Panama in 1989.
So, over the course of the 1980s,
relations between the United States and
Panama's dictator, Manuel Noriega,
deteriorated significantly. Not only did
Noriega maintain a close relationship
with Cuba, he also laundered money and
protected drug smugglers who trafficked
drugs into the United States. And since
the US interest in the Panama Canal
seemed to be threatened by Noriega's
continuing consolidation of power,
President Bush authorized an invasion of
Panama in 1989. And long story short, US
forces quickly overwhelmed the
Panamanian military and captured
Noriega. And as a result, the US
installed an American-friendly president
in Panama, as was its custom. And then,
the second military intervention was a
little more expansive, and that was the
Iraq War. So, in 1990, Iraq invaded the
small neighboring country of Kuwait in
order to control its vast oil supplies.
And they did so because after a long war
with Iran, the Iraqi economy was in
trouble and gaining control of Kuwait's
oil would help tremendously. But,
President Bush feared that if Iraq went
unopposed, Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein
would then invade Saudi Arabia, which
was a US ally, in order to gain control
of their oil as well. And therefore,
Bush issued a deadline for Hussein to
withdraw from Kuwait and when Hussein
let that deadline pass without
retreating, Bush launched Operation
Desert Storm. And to put it mildly, the
US military stormed the crap out of
those Iraqi deserts because the conflict
lasted only 100 hours and was
exceedingly effective. And soon
thereafter, Iraq withdrew its troops
from Kuwait, although Hussein was
permitted to remain in power. And that
decision would lead to a second war with
Iraq under the administration of George
W. Bush. The point is after the Cold
War, US military engagements were no
longer planned and justified by the
existential threat of communism. Rather,
the US flexed its military might in
order to keep its own political and
economic interests safe across the
globe. And once the 21st century
arrived, emphasis took on strong tones
of combating terrorism, but I'll talk
about that in another video. And then
the second effort to maintain post-Cold
War interests including forging new
diplomatic relationships. For example,
in the 1992 presidential election,
Democrat Bill Clinton pledged to focus
more on domestic issues, but he also
took significant steps to settle
long-term international conflicts and
human rights issues that threatened the
peace and security of a globalized
world. And to that end, Clinton threw
his support behind a set of agreements
known as the Oslo Accords in 1993, which
laid a path toward peace for the Middle
East. You see, for most of the second
half of the 20th century, Palestinians
and Israelis have been engaged deadly
and destructive conflicts over who had
the rightful authority to claim the land
in which they both live. And so, in the
Oslo Accords, the Palestinian Liberation
Organization agreed that Israelis ought
to be able to live in peace while
Israelis agreed to the same principle in
reverse. However, both sides continued
to violate the agreement and despite
Clinton's efforts to broker a further
peace, the conflict between these two
groups continued. But even so, the point
is is that this is just one illustration
of the way the United States applied its
power and status as the world superpower
in a world where the Cold War rivalry
had passed away. Well, okay, you can
click here to watch my other Unit 9
videos or you can click here to grab my
A Push Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to get a five on
your exam in May. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch on the flip flop.
Heimler out.